

# **AURICÉLIA BESSA**

Data Engineering

+55 12 98806-0653

teiabessa@hotmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/teia-bessa

https://github.dev/teiabessa/

## **SUMMARY**

I am a computer scientist with over 20 years of experience in the aerospace and healthcare industries. I have extensive expertise in software engineering, with proficiency in multiple programming languages, databases and project management. Currently, I have been specialized in data engineering, getting certifications and developing practical projects using technologies such as Python, Apache Spark, AWS, Azure and others.

## **EDUCATION**

IDIOMATICH English School
Advanced Level (currently studying to achieve

TOEFL certification)

**Paulista University** 

Bachelor's Degree in Computer Science (1999-2003)

**High School ETEP** 

Computer Technician (1994-1998)

## CERTIFICATIONS

- AZURE Data Engineering (until September)
- Project Management, Emotional Intelligence, and Coaching
- Python Specialization by Massachusetts Institute of Technology
- SQL SERVER
- AWS
- Terraform
- Do-178 (Washington DC)

# TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Data Engineering: Lakehouses, Data Lakes, Data Warehouses, ETL, ELT, AWS Full Stack, Azure Full Stack, Spark, PySpark, Google Colab, Databricks Spark, Terraform.
- DBA: SQL Server, MySQL, Postgre, NoSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Oracle, Sybase.
- Software Engineering and Development: Python, SQL, Java, Javascript, C, C++, PHP, Visual Basic, Delphi, Fortran, Pascal.
- PPM Tools: JIRA, Trello.
- Data Analytics and CRM tools: Google Analytics, RD Station.
- Business Intelligence and Reporting Tools: Power BI, Crystal Reports, Access, Excel.

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

### **Data Engineering**

Carrer Transition | October 2023 - Actual

- Big Data and Data Lakes Projects: Designed and implemented various projects, including:
  - o Built virtual machines on AWS EC2, loaded files onto AWS S3, and published them.
  - o Created and managed data sources on Redshift Data Warehouse and integrated them with Power BI.
  - o Developed tools in Python using Google Colab, integrating with PostgreSQL, RDS (Relational Database Service), and AWS S3.
  - o Created a Databricks Spark cluster, used notebooks to load batch files on PySpark data frames.
- Database Management: Created and manipulated databases such as Redis, MongoDB, SQL Server, NoSQL, and PostgreSQL on AWS EC2.
- Azure Experience: Developed Lakehouses and Spark pipelines.

## **Business Management and Software Engineer**

In Pulse | 2015 - 2023

- Gained valuable experience in the commercial department, enhancing communication skills, acquiring sales techniques, and assuming leadership roles. Supervised teams and promoted their professional development.
- Developed a customized system using PHP and MySQL to oversee micro and macro operations within the company, streamlining processes through agile methodology. Contributed to a 20% increase in sales rates by implementing Business Intelligence methodologies, utilizing ETL processes, and analyzing indicators in Power BI.

#### System Developer

Embraer | 1999 - 2009

- BDI Team Contribution: Played a key role in designing and implementing one of Embraer's most complex engineering systems, managing over 6 billion aircraft data from flight tests, campaigns, maneuvers. Utilized data modeling and technologies such as Sybase and Oracle databases, ColdFusion, and C++. This system continues to be used today, significantly contributing to the standardization, automation, and reduction of operational time within the division.
- Innovative Solution for CAFM System: Designed an innovative solution for the CAFM System of Performance Engineering, using Tomcat, MySQL, and ColdFusion. This resulted in a 90% reduction in operating time and software licensing costs, optimizing the company's financial resources.
- **System Integration**: Effectively contributed to the integration of systems from different areas using data integration, web services, and SAP features.